It's so hot...
Good morning.
Thank you for riding with us.
I'm supposed to be in
the System Division, but...
Lately all I do is help out in the field.
Could it be...
There's some other motive behind this...
N-no way...
It's just training, right?
To learn how operations work...
♫ July: station staff at Fukuzumi
♫ Second half: mad train modifications
♫ August: conductor training course
♫ The Kraepelin test was brutal
♫ September: conductor practicum
♫ First day and it's a just-go-for-it schedule
This train will go as far as it can.
♫ Tyurya tyurya tyurya...
Please be aware that the train type,
arrival times, and connections may change.
♫ October: conductor
♫ Tyurya rya
Yeah... this is definitely a demotion, isn't it?
Good morn--
Huh...?
The System Division, after so long, was completely empty.
The attendance log... let's see.
Lt. Commander is on leave at Risa.
Hey--
Ahh, an endless-summer resort... nice...
Huh?
Tarumi-senpai's name isn't here...
"Akane, did you hear?"
"They say there's a ghost train."
Don't tell me she ran off chasing that ghost train rumor...
Morning...
Oh, Section Chief.
Good morning.
Um...
Sorry about the short notice, but...
And so, I was seconded to a subsidiary.
Well, I did get the title of "Senior Staff,"
so the cushy transfer isn't all bad.
This room all the way in the back is Development Section 1.
Hey there.
Good morning.
'Sup.
Yo.
Hey.
'Ey.
Ah...
...hey.
...whoa!?
Hmm?
(Yuina) Pshhh! Clackety-clack!
(Akane) Oh!
(Yuina) Oh!
So you got seconded too, Senpai?
Cardan drive is nice, but you
really can't beat nose-suspended!
Huh?
What!?
You love the sound of a DMH-17 engine!?
You get it! You really get it!
(Akane) This person has gone completely off the rails.
(Yuina) I actually have a KiHa 20 in preservation on my home siding!
(Yuina) The sound is just amazing!
No...
It seems she's not the only one
who's derailed around here.
How did it come to this...
Senpai, this isn't a train yard.
It's a subsidiary.
Give me a straight answer!
Huh?
Can you really have this
running by end of next month?
We'll do our best.
(Katsuragi) That goes without sayin'!
(Yuina) Deputy Manager Yumesaki--
(Yuina) --is getting chewed out again...
(Katsuragi) Can you do it or can't you!
(Akane) The one yelling is our General Affairs director, right?
(Yumesaki) We'll do our best. (Katsuragi) That's a given!
(Yuina) Yeah, he's the client for this project.
(Yumesaki) By the go-live date...
(Akane) Ah...
(Katsuragi) Well!?
(Yuina) Even so...
(Yuina) That attitude toward a subsidiary, though?
(Yumesaki) By the go-live date... (Katsuragi) So it'll be done, yeah?
Like I'd trust that!
I'm terribly sorry...
Just 'cause you're a subsidiary
don't mean you can slack off!
The whole company's paying for this!
I'm terribly sorry...
Does being the parent company
really make you that important...?
Oh, Akane?
Um...
A development project this big--
How come it didn't go through
the System Division?
Huh...
Did I say something weird...?
Well, to begin with...
Part of it was the System Division getting
sidelined after the XP incident, but...
Originally, this was supposed to be
an easy project.
The plan was simply to customize
a product called Kinoko Workflow
for the General Affairs department
and roll it out.
But midway through the project,
things took a dramatic turn.
Someone who can't read the room
started pushing a "logical" argument,
insisting it be deployed
to every department.
Great idea!
On top of that, the majority of employees--
demanded the adoption of
Takenoko Groupware instead.
The rest, as you can imagine--
A pointless turf war.
In the end, Team Takenoko won big.
They were hopelessly outnumbered.
All the work done so far?
Completely scrapped.
However, Kinoko Workflow had
some features too good to throw away,
so they forced a merger.
Then related systems got absorbed too.
And on top of everything,
by executive decree--
"Move it to the cloud!"
And so, the project is now a raging dumpster fire.
Sparkle!
Anyway, it goes live next month! Got it!?
Wait... don't tell me the deadline
is still the original one...
Bingo.
Deadlines don't get extended.
You can't defy the parent company.
A system just needs to work, right?
You'll regret that in about eight years.
Not my pro-blem!
Ah...
Oh...
That famous ghost train rumor...
could it be...
The horror here...
...is worse than any ghost.
Well, well.
Found an SQL injection
vulnerability.
This is...
Information that shouldn't be visible
is showing up...
In fact, they probably don't even
understand the business requirements...
S-Q-L In-what-tion?
What's that? Some kind of train?
Shall I send you
to the scrap line?
Not the scrap line! No!
I don't wanna be bulldozer food!
Good morning.
Good MOHAning, SuHaFu!
My junior's transformation has me all ORONErvous!
Hiya! I'm Senior Staff Yuina Tarumi!
(Yuina) Ahahahahaha!
(Akane) *kick*
(Yuina) OW-OW-MAITE-TE-TE...!
So, Senior Staff Tarumi--
Have you ever heard of
SQL injection?
Akane, you're no fun.
Senior Staff Hosono, you're no fun.
SQL In-whatever-tion, huh...
Oh! I think I saw it on
the IT certification exam!
That's it.
I only saw it, okay?
I don't understand SQL at all!
She really does sneak in station names
at every opportunity...
And you call yourself an engineer!?
In upstream processes you don't
need to write code, so it's fine!
No, it is NOT fine!
Daishōgun? Arima Onsen-guchi?
Okay, forget SQL for now--
Let me explain injection attacks
in general terms.
First, let's say this is the world
inside an anime that you like, Senpai.
Let's say it is!
Here we have a script.
Ooh...
It's like nothing of this world.
There's a blank field in it.
You can write any dialogue you want!
Yes. You can write any text you want.
And whatever you write will happen.
Yay!
Akane: "The Montreal monorail!"
What are you making me say?
Is that really the worst you can do with it?
Hmm...
With just dialogue, you can't do much...
Akane: "For example, you can do this."
Hey, that's cheating!
A closing quote!
At that moment, Yuina, seized by an impulse,
suddenly dashes out of the room.
Wha--hey!
When Yuina returned, she was holding
a baked sweet potato.
Yuina: "Did someone order a sweet potato?"
Akane: "Ahh, this potato is so warm and fluffy..."
So, well, that's basically how it works.
This sweet potato
is actually pretty good.
This sweetness...
It's from Tokushima!
She really doesn't miss a trick, does she?
I went all the way to the Seaside Route
to buy them!
Thanks.
Anyway, as I was saying...
Finish eating first...
So basically, if you write a closing quote,
you can write stage directions too.
Yes.
Yuina obtains a
train driver's license!
Yuina acquires
another KiHa 20!
Why not just write "deadline extended"?
Better yet, "project canceled"...
Just do your actual work!
You can rewrite the world however you want,
and find out anything you want to know!
That's basically unauthorized access
to the laws of the universe.
I mean, the fact that it even lets you
enter quotation marks--
It's just stupid design, right?
Exactly.
That is a vulnerability
to injection attacks.
The same thing happens with computers.
If an injection attack gets through--
your data can be stolen
or your system can be exploited.
Like making your senpai run errands for you.
To prevent being exploited,
no matter what text is entered--
you need to make sure it doesn't
cause the system to malfunction.
So with that said, Shimoyama-san,
please rewrite this code
to use DbParameter.
If you would, thanks!
No can do.
No can do...
*sigh*...
Things don't work like they used to, do they?
By the way...
I wonder if those two are doing all right.
Something about this whole situation is off.
First, the Corporate Planning department
pushing through unrealistic scope and schedules.
And the General Affairs director
fixated on the original go-live date...
Even this isn't enough to convince them...
In that case...
How did it go? With the CIO?
I finally found out.
The General Affairs director was told
to keep this project on schedule--
directly by the president himself.
That power-tripping director...
And the president, for his part,
apparently already committed to end-of-next-month.
In a magazine interview, no less.
Always trying to save face...
All that does is make the failure
even more public.
Public...!
Even now, we should transfer
the project to our division...!
At this point,
swapping leadership is too risky.
Let's work on convincing everyone
to go with a phased rollout instead.
Tarumi, Hosono--
Please...
Stay safe...
I can't couple anymore...
The more I investigated,
the more abnormal this project turned out to be.
Less than two months until go-live.
And yet, they haven't even
nailed down the goal.
Bugs? Everyone just looks the other way...
If we just call in Lt. Commander, everything'll work out...
Absolutely not.
That person's code is so messy
it should be in the Guinness records.
Just "working" isn't good enough.
The one who'll suffer is future me.
I have a dream.
Someday, I'll live
an easy, lazy life,
sprawled out on a couch--
the dream of becoming a couch potato!
And for that dream, the first priority
is to nail down the project goals.
Deputy Manager Yumesaki!
Cutting the supplementary report feature
entirely... I'm not on board with that.
Yes, personally I agree with you.
However, Assistant Station Master Tsukita--
Are you aware of the current state
of the project?
Of course, I've heard about it, but...
Were you aware that from
the Kyoki Railway labor union--
three people have already been
hospitalized?
Oh, ah...
For the union, forcing people
to keep going in this situation--
would look bad,
wouldn't it?
Ah... yes...
Actually, there's a way to deliver the
feature you want without building it now,
and without cutting it either.
Would you be willing to help me
strategize on how to make it happen?
Please!
Of course!
(Tsukita) H-Hosono...
(Tsukita) P-please, raise your head.
(Hiroka) Looks like it's going well.
The groundwork went
extremely smoothly.
At every workplace I'd been rotated through,
there was always a key person behind the scenes.
Funny, that.
It's almost as if someone
had planned it all along.
Deputy Manager Yumesaki.
The requirements definition
that was stalled is now complete.
What do you think?
Honestly? It's hopeless.
Given the current state,
it'll take another two or three years.
So here's my proposal.
We split the development into phases--
and for this release, prioritize the core modules
and security-related development.
In Phase 1, we give up on custom forms
and use the standard free-text feature instead...
I see...
It was impossible all along...
(Akane) Deputy Manager!
(Yuina) Yumesaki-san!
(Subordinate) Huh, what?
(Subordinate) The deputy manager! The deputy manager!
(Subordinate) Wait, are you okay!?
And with that, the team's morale
plummeted to rock bottom.
Akane, it's over. I can't do this anymore.
Almost everyone's out sick.
Progress has ground to a halt...
It's completely over...
I know.
There's no choice left
but to cancel this project.
Rather than leave behind a disaster
of a garbage system,
we should end it now, with our own hands--
We can't!
If it fails, we'll be stuck
at this subsidiary forever...
No... we'll be made scapegoats,
and fired by next month.
Forget eight years from now--
I'm worried about next month.
That's right.
I gave in to temptation.
Ah...
"This is Fleet Command."
"Return to base immediately."
Farewell, maintainability.
It's fine.
A system just needs to work.
That's all.
State the nature of the emergency.
Lt. Commander!
Huh...!?
Lt. Commander...!
Kalash, it is time to rise!
So fast!
A-amazing!
Holy crap.
What incredible speed...!
That Guinness record is no joke!
Heh. A Guinness record is merely a decoration!
Whoa... incredible...
It's goto art!
Wha--!? She's writing in machine language!?
Behold-- the Low-Maintainability Code Master!
That's insane.
Oh no...
How are we supposed to test this...
No worries.
I brought along the ultimate
testing weapon!
Where am I?
Akane!?
You look terrible. Are you okay...?
Oh, um, yeah...
That's--!
The one who caused the big incident
in Episode 1--
The one who can make
any program crash--
The Ultimate Bug Trigger!
No time to waste!
Let's do this!
Great work out there!
I hear even the General Affairs director was pleased.
Heh heh.
Ha ha...
Section Chief!
It's been a full year since the OS
went out of support!
We need to update it immediately!
We can't.
That's a no-go.
You read my report
on the security issues, right!?
I did, but if we update the OS--
for some reason, that system stops working.
We're looking into a solution, but...
But we're running out of time to stall!
*sigh*...
If only we had the source code--
or at least the detailed design documents,
it would help...
Wait, there aren't any!?
Well, I had a feeling
this was going to happen
all along...
Let's just hope nothing happens...
Section Chief Hosono!
It's happened.
Ahh...
What have I done
to my future self eight years from now?
Even if that is our future...
The future can always
be changed.
Don't you think so,
Ensign?
Huh?
Yeah.
The future...
...can be changed.